foreign
[Music]
world every patient with a life limiting
illness would receive optimal hospice
and palliative care such that no one
would ever wish to hasten their own
death
unfortunately the reality is that
despite our best efforts some with
terminal illness continue to suffer
leading increasing number of patients
across the country
to explore vsed to escape intolerable
suffering voluntarily stopping eating
and drinking
some of the pros include dying at home
which is what most people's preferences
you don't have to you know spend your
fleeting hours dealing with you know
doctors and lawyers there's no waiting
period in Oregon for example their death
With Dignity act requires a 15-day
waiting period before you can get
physician assistance whereas choosing to
stop eating and drinking would seem to
afford more control I mean even just
knowing it's an option can be a comfort
those who learn about vscd may feel
empowered by the knowledge that they can
choose this option without seeking
anyone's permission because it's legal
it can be openly discussed just knowing
that there's a way out can provide
relief from feelings of desperation and
entrapment and the feeling of control
May itself be therapeutic it can also
prevent people from you know
contemplating a more violent way out and
patients don't have to feel pressured to
end their life prematurely while they
still can
physician assisted death With Dignity
laws require patients to take the lethal
drug cocktail themselves
if you have ALS and are worried about
losing your muscular function you might
feel the need to end your life before
you're ready while you still have the
capacity in fact Dr kevorkian's first
was a woman diagnosed with Alzheimer's
who wanted to end it before it got too
late potentially depriving her and her
family of years she might have you know
still been able to enjoy
and while physician assisted suicide
entails a single instantaneous and
irrevocable act death from vsed
occurs over several days allowing you
know time for a patient to change their
mind and for healing goodbyes
uh but what does it actually like
there's lots of anecdotes you know
floating around describing death in the
SED is a peaceful painless and dignified
fortunately the evidence is more than
just anecdotal there have been several
independent studies so let's look at the
data
average time of death
after stopping eating and drinking was
about seven days though eight percent
lasted more than two weeks
and how was it ask a hundred hospice
nurses and on a scale of zero a very bad
death to nine a very good death the
average score the quality of these
deaths is rated by the nurses was eight
the researchers concluded that people
usually die a good death within two
weeks after stopping food and fluids
according to the nurses reading those
last days of life is peaceful with low
levels of pain and suffering more so
even than those who chose
physician-assisted suicide this was in
Oregon so patients could have chosen
that instead but nearly twice as many
patients decided instead to take matters
into their own hand by voluntarily
stopping eating and drinking
interestingly loved ones seem to agree
with voluntary refusal food and fluids
perceived as carrying less emotional
baggage for the family more Letting Go
than taking more active approach
studying the Netherlands that
interviewed confidants like friends and
family that witnessed it found that most
considered it quote unquote dignified
death
hospice Physicians seem to agree with
nearly 90 percent surveyed reporting
that their vsed patients experienced
peaceful and comfortable deaths
state of terminal dehydration may even
have some analgesic effects and pain
killing effects presumed to be due to
the release of endorphins which act as
natural pain blockers so concluded this
review vscd May reflect all 12
principles of a good death retaining
control and dignity
one of the most famous accounts was Dr
David Eddie's description of his own
Mother's vscd my mother
was elated the next day happened to be
her
85th birthday which we celebrated with a
party balloons and all she was beaming
from ear to ear she had done it she had
found the way she uh relished her last
piece of chocolate and then stopped
eating and drinking over the last four
days my mother greeted her visitors with
first smiles she had shown for months
she energetically reminisced about the
great time she had had about all the
things she was proud of she especially
hoped I would tell you about her
traveling alone across Africa at the age
of 70 and surviving a capsized raft on
Wyoming Snake River at 82. she also
found a calming self-acceptance in
describing things in which she was not
proud
she slept between visits but woke up
brightly whenever she was touched
to share more of her memories and to say
a few more things she wanted us to know
on the fifth day it was more difficult
to wake her when we would take her hand
she would open her eyes and smile but
yeah she was too drowsy and weak to talk
very much on the sixth day we could not
wake her her face was relaxed and her
natural smile she was breathing unevenly
but peacefully we held her hands for
another two hours until she died
without hoarding pills
without making me into a criminal
without putting a bag over her head
without huddling in a van with a carbon
monoxide machine
she had found a way to bring her life
gracefully to a close
write about this David to tell others
how well this worked for me I'd like
this to be my gift
whether they are terminally ill in
intractable pain or like me just just
knowing that the you know right time has
come for them more people might want to
know that this way exists and maybe more
Physicians will help them find it
[Music]
thank you